Cryo-electron tomography turns raw movies of a cell
into molecular maps inside that cell.
Normally it's a week of babysitting a dozen tools.
Here — you hand it off.
First checkpoint. It doesn't ask you to trust it —
it shows you:
every tomogram reconstructed, one QC agent each,
a handedness check so downstream poses aren't mirrored.
Ten of ten. You sign off.
Next checkpoint: it finds the molecules.
Template matching, scored —
and the QC tells good tomograms from bad: here the picks
follow the cell; there, the strongest hits sit on an ice
edge — so that tomogram is out.
Then the same tools, a new config, no new code —
and it finds a second, much rarer machine,
at ninety-seven-percent recall.
The payoff checkpoint.
Which of these twenty blobs are real ribosomes?
One score would mislead you — a low-res template loves
a smooth blob, and ranks the sharpest maps last.
So it brings four measurements, mostly template-free,
and shows you where they agree and where they fight.
It names the confident core, flags the ambiguous cluster —
instead of hiding it. Then it steps back. You decide.
Resolution, measured honestly — the mask can fake signal,
so it randomizes the phases and subtracts that off.
Then both molecules go into one refinement population,
so the tilt-series model is solved with every particle
from both —
ribosomes anchor the geometry, and the rare species
rides along.
The result: a ribosome at seven-point-eight ångströms,
and fatty-acid synthase at fourteen — its D-three barrel, resolved.
Then both maps go back where they live — every molecule,
at its pose, inside the cell.
Molecular sociology, read straight off the data.
State on disk, not chat. Gates for judgment.
An agent you supervise — not a script you babysit.